<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the publique fast the twelfth day of April. At St. Maries Oxford, before the members of the honourable House of Commons there assembled; by Henry Ferne D.D. And printed by their order.</title>
            <author>Ferne, H. (Henry), 1602-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85235</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872019</idno>
  <idno type="VID">154492</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240939328</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F805</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E46_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23506</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872019</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99872019e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85235)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154492)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 8:E46[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the publique fast the twelfth day of April. At St. Maries Oxford, before the members of the honourable House of Commons there assembled; by Henry Ferne D.D. And printed by their order.</title>
                  <author>Ferne, H. (Henry), 1602-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Leonard Lichfield, printer to the Vniversity,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford [i.e. London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The imprint is false. "A London counterfeit issued probably on May 7"--Madan.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 8th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible. --  O.T. --  Judges V, 15 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Fast-day sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154492:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154492:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> SERMON PREACHED AT THE PUBLIQUE FAST The Twelfth day of <hi>April. At</hi> S<seg rend="sup">t</seg> MARIES <hi>OXFORD,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BEFORE THE MEMBERS OF THE HONOURABLE HOUSE OF COMMONS There Assembled;</p>
            <p>By <hi>Henry Ferne D. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Printed by their Order.</p>
            <q>Every Kingdome divided against it selfe is brought to desolation. <bibl>
                  <hi>MAT. 12.25.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>If ye bite and devoure one another, take heed ye be not consumed one of another. <bibl>
                  <hi>GAL. 5.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>OXFORD, Printed by LEONARD LICHFIELD, Printer <hi>to the Vniversity,</hi> 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order_to_print">
            <pb facs="tcp:154492:2"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Die Veneris 12. Aprilis. 1644.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>ORdered by the Members of the Commons House of Parliament As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled at</hi> Oxford, <hi>That Colonell</hi> Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mull, <hi>and Master</hi> Alestree, <hi>give Doctor</hi> Ferne <hi>Thanks for his Sermon, and desire him the same may be Printed.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Noah Bridges.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154492:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JUDGES 5. V. 15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>For the Divisions of Reuben there were great Thoughts of heart <hi>(or as it is Vers. 16.)</hi> great searchings of heart.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Song of <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Barak,</hi> saith the Title of the Chapter, and out of a Song to chuse you a Text for a day of Humiliation, may seeme an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hasty providing for your joy, rather then a seasonable enforcement of your sorrow; <hi>Debo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> and <hi>Barak</hi> are in their triumph, and well they might, God had delivered them, and restored their Peace: We are under the pressure, and if their joy suit not with our present conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it will with our desires, with that expectation wee have of an happy Issue, in order to which we afflict our soules now, and hang downe our heads this day, that God in his good time may lift them up.</p>
            <p>They that are truely thankefull and glad upon a deliverance, do looke backe to dangers they have past, and can at once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in what straits they were, and by whose default or trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery brought into them, and by whose ayd they have escaped them. All this here. <hi>Divisions,</hi> and upon them <hi>great thoughts of heart,</hi> and again <hi>Divisions,</hi> and upon them <hi>great searchings of heart:</hi> a matter it was of dangerous consequence; <hi>Reuben</hi> and <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Asser</hi> are noted for them. It would have gone ill with <hi>Israel,</hi> had other Tribes forborn too, had not the Lord moved the hearts of some to come in to the help, and by them given the Victory.</p>
            <p>There were <hi>Divisions,</hi> &amp; upon them <hi>great thoughts of heart;</hi> so they, in the joyfull remembrance of what was past; There are <hi>Divisions</hi> among us, and upon them great heart-burnings,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:154492:3"/>high swelling thoughts; so have wee cause to complaine in the sense of our present Condition; and cause also to entertain other kind of <hi>Thoughts,</hi> such as make for Peace: <hi>Thoughts,</hi> and <hi>sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings of heart,</hi> why is it thus with us? what shall we doe for the closing up of these <hi>Divisions?</hi> That wee also may come to the joy and triumph of this Song, in a gratefull remembrance of what was, and what might have hapned upon our <hi>Divisions. For the Divisions of Reuben there were great thoughts, great searchings of heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Text is short and quick, as usually the words of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors are, and generally all the expressions of this song. It admits therfore severall readings; the <hi>Chaldee</hi> Paraphrase ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the meaning of it thus, <hi>In seminibus Reuben multi insidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores cordis, In the lines or families of Reuben there were many double hea ted, devling perfidiously.</hi> It is a truth indeed, that in hard and dangerous times (such as these were) there are alwaies some by whose treachery and perfidious dealing <hi>Divisions</hi> are caused and fomented: some notorious above others, that deserve to have a mark set upon them, and to be Chronicled for it, as <hi>Reuben</hi> here; <hi>Hierome</hi> reads it thus, <hi>Diviso in se Reuben, mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimorum reperta est contentio,</hi> which gives us this sence, When a people fals into <hi>Divisions,</hi> there are always some great and hot spirits that enflame the contention, and make it not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily to be appeased. Other Interpreters read it otherwise. But least I seem to shew you the <hi>Division</hi> of Interpreters rather then of <hi>Reuben,</hi> I find the most and best of them render it according to the Originall, as our Translation hath it, <hi>in,</hi> or, <hi>for the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of Reuben there were Magnae imaginationes, sculpturae</hi> or, <hi>decreta cordis;</hi> in the Hebrew, <hi>Chikkee; Thoughts of heart,</hi> in our Text; or <hi>Impressions,</hi> as in the margine. Then to insinuate the dangerous consequence of this, and how much they were to blame that were guilty of it, it's repeated again in the next <hi>verse</hi> with the change but of one letter for the greater elegancy of the song, <hi>Magnae investigationes, Chikree,</hi> saith the Hebrew, <hi>great searchings of heart,</hi> as it is in ours. The <hi>Reubenites</hi> were divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from their Brethren in the time of distresse, and therefore great exceptions and resolutions were taken against them for it; <hi>For the divisions of Reuben, there were great thoughts, great searchings of heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:154492:3"/>
            <p>We wil consider this first in the History, then as concerning us and our condition.</p>
            <p>Thrice I find <hi>Reuben</hi> chalenged upon this point of <hi>division,</hi> and thereupon great thoughts, jealousies, and exceptions.</p>
            <p>First, in the matter of their lot and inheritance. In that they were divided from their Brethren, the River <hi>Iordan</hi> was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them; &amp; when they first desired it, <hi>Num.</hi> 32. <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>Let this land be given us for a possession, and bring us not over this Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan,</hi> great <hi>thoughts</hi> there were, and <hi>searchings of heart</hi> upon it, <hi>Moses</hi> is very hot with them upon a mistake of their intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as if they meant to separate from their Brethren, and not beare the common burden of the war with them: <hi>shall your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> (saith he) <hi>go up to war, and ye sit here?</hi> vers. 6. <hi>wherefore discourage ye the hearts of the Children of Israel? vers</hi> 7. Thus did thoughts and Jealousies arise, till their harmlesse intentions were known; upon the clearing of which, <hi>Moses</hi> is satisfied, &amp; upon the performance of them. <hi>Ioshua</hi> sends the <hi>Reubenites</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with a blessing. <hi>Iosh.</hi> 22.6.</p>
            <p>They are no sonner quit of this, but they give a second occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of Offence in the matter of Religion. In their returne they build an Altar upon the bankes of <hi>Iordan,</hi> as if they meant to be <hi>divided</hi> in worship from their Brethren. So it is taken, and thereupon <hi>great thoughts and searchings of heart,</hi> Josh. 22. They are charged with Idolatry, <hi>is the iniquity of</hi> Peor <hi>too li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle?</hi> ver. 17. and are threatned with warre for it, <hi>the whole Congregation gathered themselves together; to get up to warre against them,</hi> vers. 12.</p>
            <p>Very nice and tender we find them in the point of worship, the raising of an Altar (and good reason for it) yet ready to receive satisfaction; their zeale is forward, yet not so heady as to run streight into Action, and use those Armes they had taken, before they fully understood what their Brethren meant; lest peradventure it might be their owne misgrounded jealousie, which they revenged upon their Brethren, and not any just of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence given by them. Therefore <hi>Phineas</hi> the Priest, and ten Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, from every Tribe one, are sent unto them to chalenge them for it, and receive their answer, which is this: that the Altar is not raised for a Sacrifice, but for a witnesse and remembrance
<pb facs="tcp:154492:4"/>to what God and People the <hi>Renbenites</hi> belonged; and so wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not so much an argument of their <hi>dividing</hi> from, as a monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Communion with their Brethren in the same Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and worship. All parts are pleased and God is blessed, <hi>vers.</hi> 33. Had the zeale of these daies been of such a temper, so capable of satisfaction, the businesse had not come to Armes, but we had still agreed as Brethren, and had still cause to blesse God for the continuance of our Peace and happinesse.</p>
            <p>Lastly, we find <hi>Reuben</hi> with other Tribes charged here in this place, for <hi>dividing</hi> from their Brethren in a Time of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresse, of which they cannot cleare themselves, but must stand registred and noted to Posterity as guilty of great unfaithfulnes, and not without cause. The danger was great, the distresse ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, it required all the power and strength their Brethren could make, <hi>For the high waies were unoccupied, Travellers walked through by-waies,</hi> vers. 6. <hi>The Inhabitants of the Villages cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed.</hi> ver. 7. <hi>Warre was in the gates,</hi> and yet scarce <hi>a shield or speare to be found among forty thousand,</hi> vers. 8. An hard case when the Enemy is in the Field, and Princes with the People adhering to them, are in such a condition, so unprovided.</p>
            <p>For this, <hi>Deborah</hi> calls <hi>Barak</hi> to blow the Trumpet, set up the Standard, to invite all, as they were bound, to come in with helpe. She blesses some for comming; <hi>My heart is towards the Governours of Israel, that offered themselves willingly,</hi> vers. 9. she notes others for not comming, curses others for more wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full forbearance. <hi>Reuben, Dan</hi> and <hi>Asser</hi> are noted for not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming; <hi>Reuben</hi> liked the bleatings of the flock better then the noise of the Battell, <hi>vers.</hi> 16. <hi>Dan</hi> got himselfe into ships to flye from that Army he should have appeared against, and <hi>As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser</hi> stayed in his owne ruinous breaches to defend what he had at home, <hi>vers.</hi> 17. All these were farther of, and had their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate reasons of absence, yet ought they to have performed their duty to the publique, though with their owne losse and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard; and because they did not, <hi>great thoughts and searchings of heart,</hi> great displeasure conceived against them.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Meroz</hi> is cursed, <hi>vers.</hi> 23. and that not out of stomack and a distempered desire of revenge, as we commonly vent our anger against those that answer not our expectation, but <hi>dicit
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:154492:4"/>Angelus Domini,</hi> the Lord will have them cursed, because be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neare at hand, within hearing of the Battell, they came not out to helpe, could have no pretence but plaine disaffection. Though she leaves not <hi>Reuben</hi> under a Curse, yet under a black note set upon him and others for so great unfaithfulnesse, by reason of which, if the Lord had not stirred up other Tribes to offer themselves willingly, it might have gone ill with <hi>Israel.</hi> And therefore, <hi>For the divisions of</hi> Reuben <hi>there were great thoughts, great searchings of heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus in the History. Now read we the Text in our selves &amp; consider what we have to doe, if we desire the happy issue, that <hi>Deborah</hi> &amp; <hi>Barak</hi> had notwithstanding these <hi>Divisions.</hi> Look we therefore upon our <hi>Divisions</hi> how they stand; and then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine wee our <hi>Thoughts,</hi> how we are affected upon these our <hi>Divisions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thoughts</hi> and <hi>Divisions</hi> are the two hinges upon which this Text and all our distractions doe turne. <hi>Thoughts</hi> beget <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions,</hi> and these againe produce greater Thoughts. Men are first <hi>divided</hi> in Opinion by mistakes and errour, then in Affection, by Jealousies and displeasure; and being so parted, goe farther asunder by greater misconceits, censurings and heart-burnings; and so it will be, so long as we consult with flesh and blood: for <hi>whence come Wars</hi> and <hi>fightings amongst you?</hi> (saith St Iam. 4.1.) <hi>come they not hence? even of your lusts that war in your Members?</hi> And while corruption breaths out our thoughts and Resolutions, <hi>divisions</hi> will not cease; there must be new <hi>search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the heart,</hi> for new thoughts and resolutions; not such as corrupt nature suggests upon <hi>divisions</hi> and discords, but such as better instruction, and a due sence of our sad condition may prompt us with.</p>
            <p>First, of our <hi>divisions,</hi> and of them not so much to tel you the miseries come upon Civill discord and <hi>division:</hi> what neede I tell you what you feel? you know them too well by suffering; but of them so far forth, as may better conduce to the direction of our <hi>Thoughts,</hi> that every heart may know what it is guilty of, what it may seare, what it should seek for redresse.</p>
            <p>If we look into State or Church, we may see in what condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion we are. Moe Tribes stand <hi>divided</hi> from their Soveraign &amp;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154492:5"/>their duty, then are here noted by <hi>Deborah;</hi> nay the <hi>Reubenites</hi> themselves, the first born of the People, as I may call them, the heads of the Tribes are, have been long <hi>divided</hi> among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. Scarce any private Family, but it is rent, and torne, not any bond of duty and relation, which nature, or friendship, or policy, or religion has knit but it's broken by these <hi>Divisions:</hi> in a word, the whole Kingdome divided by Faction, and the Church by Schisme, and every heart thereupon is full of thought and feare.</p>
            <p>Who they are that stand guilty of the dividing of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <hi>Deborah</hi> here gives us to understand, by that duty shee expects from all the people to come in at her call, and by that charge she layes upon them for not performing; And if they, that came not in to the help when <hi>Barak</hi> at her command blew the Trumpet, stand guilty of the <hi>Divisions,</hi> how much more they that without Authority blow a Trumpet (as <hi>Sheba</hi> did) to draw the people after them? By this we may see that there are two sorts of Subjects found guilty of our <hi>divisions,</hi> they that are contrivers and authors of the <hi>divisions</hi> themselves, and they that stand off, come not in to help at the command of the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne in these times of distresse.</p>
            <p>It is not a time this to accuse others so much as our selves, nor are we met this day to search other mens hearts, but our owne; yet sometimes <hi>this</hi> may be done the better, if <hi>that</hi> be done in some sort, and we may better know what to take to our selves as our own, when we see what belongs to others. For this wee need not search other other mens hearts but actions, and that briefly and only according to the passages of this story, the <hi>Reu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benites</hi> Lot, the <hi>Reubenites</hi> Altar, the <hi>Reubenites</hi> standing <hi>divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> from their Brethren in times of distresse.</p>
            <p>There was, as you heard, offence taken, that the <hi>Reubenites</hi> should have the first lot and inheritance, who seemed to refuse to bear the common burden of the war with their brethren; and you know who they were, that to give beginning to these <hi>divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions</hi> tooke offence, that the lot should first fall upon such, such should chiefly be respected in offices and preferments, that would not, could not (as they thought) beare the burden, but would intend their private interests, not the publique: and you
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:154492:5"/>see what they have now done themselves, they have brought up their brethren armed against us, as if we were <hi>Canaanites</hi> to to be rooted out, and have designed them Lot and inheritance on this side the River, for bearing the burden of the warre with them, if you think they have made no good application of this stroy, see if they make a better of the next.</p>
            <p>There was offence taken, as you heard, at <hi>Reubens</hi> Altar, as if it had bin raised for a new worship, &amp; arms taken to revenge the suspected idolatry; you know who they are that upon the like offence and suspition, have put the people into arms, and do maintain the fact by that designe against <hi>Reuben,</hi> as if their Jealousies and suspitions were good cause for armes, or they had the like authority and supream power as <hi>Ioshuah</hi> had, who sent <hi>Phineas</hi> the Priest with other Princes, to call the <hi>Reube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> to account, and denounce war against them.</p>
            <p>Let me here by the way say thus much for the Established Ceremonies of our Church, as the <hi>Reubenites</hi> did for their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, they are not for worship, they are for remembrance, for te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification, and outward expression of inward and invisible ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments. And for the words <hi>Altar</hi> and <hi>Table,</hi> who knows not the indifferent use of them in the ancient Church? &amp; how that Schismes and <hi>divisions</hi> (the guilt of these men) were usually expressed by that phrase <hi>of raising Altar against Altar?</hi> 'Tis true indeed that latter Times have attempted to place a proper Sacrifice there, a just cause of offence but let the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> answer for that. I find that our first Reformers having cast out that Doctaine, retained the word <hi>Altar</hi> in our Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy according to the ancient indifferent use: but I do not find it there now; happily it was taken out, to take away all shadow of offence. And I could wish, that in these times especially when every heart is so full of thoughts and Jealousies, all causes of offence and exception were taken away: but I could wish also; that they who have abused this story to abuse the People into a rebelion, would sadly consider what they have done themselves, how they have raised <hi>Altar</hi> against <hi>Altar,</hi> brought in Sect upon Sect, every one of them to have their severall interests in our <hi>divisions</hi> every one to have a finger in the sore, to keep it from closing; and what hope is left us, if Gods hand were not above all.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:154492:6"/>
            <p>Lastly, if we should goe on to <hi>search</hi> into other mens wayes, wee should finde many accessory to our <hi>Div sions,</hi> if not for raising yet for the continuance of them; Such as deserv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be noted with the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ben<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tes</hi> here, for standing <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vided</hi> from their brethren, not conmming in at the summons of Soveraigne Authority, but denying the help which the Church and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome 1. quire of them in these times of distresle. Had there not been such a generall failing in so necessary a duty, these <hi>Divisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> had not gathered such strength, nor we had cause to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, as they here, <hi>That the high wayes are unoccupied, Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellars passe through by ways; the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nhabitants of the Villages do cease;</hi> Our Towns dispeopled, our Country wasted, our houses spoiled,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 74 21.</note> our Churches prophaned; Rapine and bloodshed in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very place, and as the Psalmist, <hi>The whole Land is ful of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and cruell habitations.</hi> Such is our condition; I need not tell you what you feele, you are sensible of what you suffer by reason of these <hi>Divisions.</hi> Let us now examine, How wee are affected, what our <hi>Thoughts</hi> thereupon, which is my second Generall. The <hi>Thoughts</hi> and <hi>Impressions of heart,</hi> which are in us upon these our <hi>Divisions. For the Divisions of Reuben, there were great thoughts, great searchings of heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What <hi>Thoughts</hi> and <hi>Impressions</hi> and <hi>searchings of heart</hi> are? what should be in us upon these our <hi>Divisions?</hi> that's now our present consideration, and indeed it's the chiefe worke of the Preacher this day, not to raise some slight flitting <hi>Thoughts</hi> in your minds, as when you heare a quaint and nimble discourse: I have not now to do with the <hi>Phansie</hi> but the <hi>Heart,</hi> and to have <hi>impressions</hi> made upon that, you must endure the rougher touch of a heavier hand. There is no heart sutely so hard, but if it selfe has had some remorse, some <hi>impressions</hi> from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration of our present condition; but because they are accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to it's own temper, it is like they be not such as should be, not such as will any way help to mend the businesse; therefore <hi>Searchings of the heart</hi> there must be, that we may know what <hi>thoughts</hi> and <hi>impressions</hi> there are in our hearts, what there should be, upon the due sense of our present condition.</p>
            <p>Are they such as <hi>Esau</hi> had against his brother <hi>Iacob? The dayes of mourning will come, then wil I kil my brother: thoughts</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:154492:6"/>of revenge against those, that have supplanted, robbed, spoiled you? nor such <hi>Thoughts:</hi> or such as those stately ones had; <hi>Esa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 9.10. <hi>The bricks are fallen down, but we will build with hew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n stores; the Sycamores are cut down, but we wil ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nge them into Ced<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs: Thoughts</hi> of Pride, of repairing more sumptuonsly what you have been spoyled of? Not such <hi>Thoughts</hi> neither: or are they such as those luxurious ones had, <hi>Esay</hi> 22.12, 13. of eating and drinking and making mirth, when the Lord called for mourning? <hi>Thoughts</hi> of pleasure, to ease your restraint, and drive away the remembrance of what you have lost? No, nor such <hi>Thoughts:</hi> or such as the Disciples had when they disputed <hi>who should be the greatest</hi> in the expected Kingdome of their Master: <hi>Thoughts</hi> of Ambition, how you may attaine to greatnesse, when the Kingdome is restored? No, not such <hi>Thoughts;</hi> or lastly, have you <hi>Thoughts</hi> of purchasing your Peace at any rate, that may cost you least, how ever deare to others? Do you thinke of laying all the meanes of the Church in the gap to make it up? No, it's the way to make it wider; not any such <hi>Thoughts</hi> as these: not any <hi>Thought,</hi> whereby we seeke ourselves in p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ide, or profit, or pleasure, or revenge in these times of distresse; we must look at some higher hand then that which spoiled us, and be sensible of something else then our own losses.</p>
            <p>We remember now in the <hi>day of our affliction,</hi> as <hi>Ierusalem</hi> did in hers, <hi>our pleasant things which we had in the dayes of old, Lam.</hi> 1.7. and know whom to blame for it, that we have them not now, <hi>the Adversary that hath spread out his hand upon all our pleasant things, v.</hi> 10. These <hi>thoughts</hi> much possesse our hearts, but do we ever think of blaming our selves for it? Are wee sensible of these pressures, or look we at our losses, in relation to Gods wrath upon the Land, and our sins provoking it? That's a <hi>Thought,</hi> may be is not in every heart, yet either such a <hi>thought</hi> as that, or no hope of redre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>se.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thoughts</hi> and resolutions there must be, not such such as corrupt Nature usually breathes out, but such as a due consideration of our sad condition may suggest; <hi>Thoughts</hi> towards God, and <hi>Thoughts</hi> towards Man; all such as make for Peace, for a clos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing up of these <hi>Divisions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, towards God, as provoked to wrath, <hi>thoughts</hi> for humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation; and again, towards God, as to be appeased, as able also to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:154492:7"/>our <hi>Peace,</hi> and re-unite dis-affected hearts; <hi>thoughts</hi> for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation. The poor penitent son, <hi>Lu.</hi> 15.17. as soone as <hi>hee came to himselfe,</hi> and was able to <hi>thinke</hi> in what condition he was, sits down and communes with his owne heart, <hi>I perish here with hunger, I will arise and goe, &amp;c.</hi> there he is thinking and resolving what to do, what to say, what to desire for the easing of his misery.</p>
            <p>There must be then, 1. <hi>Thoughts</hi> upon these <hi>Divisions</hi> and Mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries as Evidences of Gods wrath towards this Land; that through the <hi>Divisions</hi> which do sunder us one from another, we may discern another breach by which we are <hi>divided</hi> from God, and in the wrath of implacable men that contend with us, we may discover a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother wrath toward us, the wrath of a displeased God. It is with us as with <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Israel, Esay</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 21. <hi>Manasseh against E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim, and Ephraim against Manasseh, and both together against Iudah.</hi> Great <hi>divisions</hi> then, all in combustion; but see what <hi>Thoughts</hi> the Prophet prompts them with in the words following, <hi>Yet for all this his anger is not turned away, but his hand is stret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out still,</hi> the wrath which they spent one upon another was his anger, and the wounds they gave one another were the stroaks of his stretched out hand. And that we may see Civil dissention is a greater judgement than forraigne invasion, and so an evidence of greater wrath, it is put here in the last place, as that which would bring them to utter Desolation, if means were not used to have <hi>that anger turned away,</hi> and that <hi>stretched out hand</hi> pulled in. They are first devoured by <hi>Syrian</hi> and <hi>Philistim, ver.</hi> 12. and the same words subjoyned, <hi>For all this his anger is not turned away, but his hand is stretched out still:</hi> to shew they should be sensible of his anger in the fury of forreigne enemies and feel his hand in their stroake; but because they did not, be laies an heavier judgement upon them, cause them to be devoured one by another, the most ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent signe of h s greatest displeasure.</p>
            <p>Many among us, I suppose, have carefully looked upon the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and progresse of these <hi>divisions,</hi> how they were raised and fomented, by whom, and by what means, but all, perchance, in a prudentiall way onely; and have observed with as watchfull an eye (as <hi>Elia'hs</hi> servant did) this cloud that hangs over our heads, how encreased from small beginnings; but not considered, perchance, what influence Heaven has had upon the raising and enlarging of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:154492:7"/>it, till it has now covered the whole Land with darknesse. Get we then up to Mount <hi>Carmel,</hi> (as <hi>Eliah's</hi> servant there) by thoughts se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>questred a while from things below, and <hi>looke seven times,</hi> consider again and again, how by degrees it has made black the Heavens, &amp; hangs over us as a fearfull signe of Gods displeasure, often breaking down upon us in showers of blood; and then thinke we have cause to make haste, as <hi>Eliah</hi> adviseth <hi>Ahab,</hi> lest the raine, the inundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Gods judgments stop us, lest his wrath through our neglect come to that height, there be no appeasing it.</p>
            <p>For heare what is threatned by the Prophet <hi>Ieremy, c.</hi> 30. <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ult. The fierce anger of the Lord shall not returne till he hath perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the intents</hi> (or as above, <hi>til he has executed the thoughts) of his heart; in the latter dayes ye shall consider it:</hi> He hath his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and <hi>thoughts of heart</hi> in all this, such as concerne the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his wrath: and our <hi>thoughts of heart</hi> should be according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that all this which is upon us, is the execution of his wrath. In the latter dayes (saith he) yee will consider so much; Oh how much better were it for us to consider it at first, than in the latter dayes; when the Lord begins to execute his wrath, then when hee has made an end, when indeed it is too late? It's the first <hi>thought</hi> we should have of these our Divisions and Miseries, as of signes and Evidences of God's wrath, which he has begun to execute up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Land.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Thoughts</hi> of Wrath provoked by our sin. Wrath for sin! Who knowes not that? I doe not undertake to tell you upon this Text what you know not, but what, perchance, you <hi>thinke</hi> not on so sadly as you should, <hi>Thoughts</hi> therefore of this Wrath for our sins; Ours, I say, who thinke (it may be) we have nothing to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer for in these <hi>Divisions:</hi> but can lay all the blame upon those we found guilty of raising or continuing them. They have indeed their speciall parts in them, and the more to answer for, and well it is that we are not to answer with them for the like guilt, as they are: but we, as we are punished by these <hi>Divisions,</hi> so have we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served it, it is not without provocation on our parts.</p>
            <p>We see a grievous pestilence sent upon the People, 2 <hi>Sam. ult.</hi> and find the immediate cause to be <hi>David's</hi> numbring of them; he takes it to himselfe, <hi>What have these sheep done? vers.</hi> 17. but these sheep as innocent as they were of the offence of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>bring be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:154492:8"/>onely passive in it, as we are this day in these Divisions, yet had they their Sins, which gave beginning to all this. <hi>David's</hi> num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring moved God to send the Pestilence, but what moved God to move, or (as the Margine notes it out of the <hi>Chronicles</hi>) suffer <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an</hi> to move <hi>David</hi> to number the People, but the number of the Peoples Sins? <hi>The anger of the Lord was kindled against Israel, vers.</hi> 1. They mov'd God to anger, and he thereupon suffers Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than to move <hi>David</hi> to number the People, that they may be lesse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and both <hi>David</hi> and People made to know themselves.</p>
            <p>So now we see the sword drawne, and as many thousands fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len by it, as by that Pestilence; we know what hand first unshea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed that Sword: but we must also consider that all of us had an hand in moving that wrath that is executed by this Sword, in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God to <hi>mingle a perverse spirit in the midst of the Land,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Is.</hi> 9.14.</note> to suffer <hi>Satan</hi> to move a company of unquiet minds, and put such <hi>thoughts</hi> into their hearts as made for <hi>Division</hi> and disturbance; and thereupon <hi>think</hi> we, unhappy men are they that ever they should be such instruments of their Countries misery: nay, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy we (should we think) that we have beene such causes of provoking Gods wrath against this Land.</p>
            <p>It is true that those unquiet Spirits stand charged with our <hi>divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions</hi> and Woes, and you know what they are guilty of at the barre of mans Justice, could they be brought thither: and that they must answer for it at Gods Tribunall: but we must also consider, that every man there stands guilty of provoking this wrath, which is pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed out upon the Land through these <hi>divisions.</hi> Even with the whole Land has the Lord a <hi>Controversie,</hi> as he had against his People. <hi>Hos</hi> 4.1. Every one to be called to the Barre, and doth it not then concerne us to be <hi>thinking</hi> what we have done, and what we shall say? Think it not enough to plead, I have been on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Passive, a sufferer in these <hi>divisions,</hi> no instrument of them: but hast thou not been active enough in sin? I have been Loyall to my Soveraigne: but hast thou not been rebellious against thy God? I hope I have a good Cause in hand: but dost thou think how thy sinfull prophanenesse and thy neglect of Gods Service, as it did its part before in provoking, so still in continuing of this wrath, still fighting against that good Cause thou pretendest to defend.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:154492:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Searchings</hi> of heart there must be for this, not such as usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally upon discord and contention, <hi>Searchings</hi> of other mens hearts, judgings, censurings; but of our owne hearts. Not to say, what meane these men to doe thus to embrue a Land in blood? thus to cast off all obedience? thus to breake all the bonds and tyes, of friendship, kindred? but to <hi>search</hi> and say, what meant we by our former disobediences and Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions against God, to provoke his fierce wrath against this Land? what meant we to breake and cast from us all the Cords and obligations he had upon us, stronger then any bond of relation or duty twixt us and those, that are nearest and dearest to us? nay what meane we still by crying sinnes to call downe more Judgements?</p>
            <p>See, what the Lords <hi>thought</hi> and purpose is when he deales with a Nation in his displeasure, that we may know what our <hi>Thoughts</hi> should be; <hi>I hearkned</hi> (saith he) <hi>and heard, but they spake not aright, no man repenteth him of his wickednesse, saying, what have I done? Ier.</hi> 8.6. God when he sends a Judgement to plead his controversie with a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, withdraws himselfe, stands as it were behind the Curtaine, the thick darknesse, to hearken and heare how they will dispute it with his Rod; that is, what <hi>Thoughts</hi> and purposes we have upon these <hi>Divisions,</hi> whether there be any that <hi>searcheth</hi> the heart to say, <hi>what have I done?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The better to prompt us to such thoughts, the Lord doth usually so proportion out the punishment, that it beares some markes and remembrances of the sinnes that caused it: See then how in mercy he has dealt with us these many yeares, and how he now deales with us accordingly in pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ishment.</p>
            <p>He had long since made up those <hi>Divisiont,</hi> which rent this Kingdom through the competition of two Houses stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for the Crowne; and after that he united the two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes which <hi>divided</hi> this I sland; which double Union toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Sea, as a wall of brasse, surrounding it, made it so entire in it selfe,
<note place="margin">Florus.</note> that (as the Historian speakes of a People enclosed with Mountaines) <hi>non videretur hostibus patere
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:154492:9"/>aditus, nisi è Caelo, aut ab inferis, venientibus: there seemed no way for Enemies to enter, unlesse they dropt out of the Clouds, or sprang up from Hell.</hi> How then is our Peace broken, our Kingdomes dis-joyned,
<note place="margin">Micha 6.</note> our Church divided! <hi>Heare the Rod,</hi> (saith the Prophet) the Rod that now scourges us has a Voyce, and tels us, we have not kept close to God, and therefore are distracted among our selves; we have not suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently prized those many deliverances through which he has brought us to this time, and therefore he now leaves us to our selves to be devoured one by another; we have not thankfully acknowledged, how he has planted us in this good Land, encreased us, given us safety from Forraigne Enemies these many yeares and ages, theresore now he makes us to know what intestine <hi>Division</hi> is; what <hi>thoughts</hi> else can we have, but that so we have deserved to be so punished?</p>
            <p>More particularly we may remember, when God had blessed both Church and State with great meanes of a flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing prosperity, how we were wantonly and needlesly then <hi>divided</hi> among our selves, about the day of worship whether it should be <hi>divided,</hi> and part of it given to sports? about the place of worship, whether thus or thus to be odor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? about some gestures and Ceremony of Worship, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thus or thus to be performed? and that to the engaging of Authority, and with such eagernesse and heat, that the <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion</hi> came to great thoughts of heart, great exasperations of mind. How is it now with us! The people fall off from the very established worship it selfe, and reproach it to the scorn of all Authority. What <hi>thoughts</hi> can we have upon this, but that it hath pleased the Lord to punish our <hi>Divisions</hi> with <hi>Devisions?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not long since we saw it in our great City as Saint <hi>Chrysostome</hi> complains it was at <hi>Antioch,</hi> when he preached there, the Theater was set against the Church, the applause in that lowder then the Psalmes in this, and the confluence of the People to the Play more Solemne, then the frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of his Auditory. So have we seen our People <hi>divided</hi> between the Church and the Play-house, between a Sermon
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:154492:9"/>too and a Masse; at the same time as great a multitude re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning from the one as from the other. And can we marvell to see our People now <hi>divided</hi> in Armes, and this Land made a Theater or Stage to act our present Tragedies on, as other Countries about us have been, for the neglect of Gods honour in the countenancing of Vertue &amp; Religion?</p>
            <p>Againe, our punishment is Warre, Civill warre or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord; Warre is the breaking of our Peace and plenty, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Warre the breach of all bonds of kindred, friendship, justice. What now speakes the Rod? what <hi>thoughts</hi> doth it prompt us with? that our quiet is disturbed, our Peace ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, because we improved not the advantage of it to his glory and Service; our plenty broken, because mis-spent; out property gone, because wee used what was his as our owne, as he complaines of his People, <hi>Hos.</hi> 2.8. that they tooke <hi>the Wine and Corne and Oyle which he gave them, and prepared them for Baal,</hi> in providing offerings thereof for that Idoll; so we the plenty he gave us, and prepared it, to <hi>make provision for our lusts,</hi> therefore now are we spoiled of our property in what we had, by them that had no right unto it. What else can we thinke?</p>
            <p>Yea, but may some say, or thinke at least, I am free from those notorious Sinnes of Excesse, upon which the blessings of Peace and Plenty have been mis-spent, <hi>Drunkennesse and riot, superfluity and vanity of apparrell, chambering and wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse;</hi> It is well if thou beest: yet so did the Pharisee justifie himselfe, I am no extortioner, no adulterer, no prophane person as this Publican; but what art thou man? Art thou as carefull of performing the duty, as of abstaining from the vice? Or doest thou not <hi>divide</hi> the two Tables, and out of a conceit of keeping the second in thine honesty to man, cast off the first in a failing of thy service to God? or having some care of the Negative part of the Commandement, doest thou not neglect the Affirmative? Let a man search his heart by this double point of the Precept (the prohibition of the sin, and the command of the duty) and he shall quickly <hi>know the plague, of his owne heart,</hi> as it is 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>8.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:154492:10"/>and as every man is bound to doe especially in these times of distresse and humiliation; and he shall finde, that if upon the first search he can say, he is free from the notorious crying sinnes of this Age; upon better <hi>searching of heart</hi> he will have cause to say; he is not free from having part in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of this Wrath, which is powred out upon this Land through these wasting <hi>Divisions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For did the best of us examine how we <hi>divide</hi> our time between his service and our owne occasions, nay pleasures and vain delights; how partially and unequally we deale with him; how much of that time which should be applied to the performance of holy Duties private and publique, we take and imploy as we list: we should not thinke it any marvell that we lose by these <hi>Divisions,</hi> when hee loses so much by out <hi>dividing</hi> with him: or that we are false among our selves, when we are not true to him; we have not hearkened to his call, who would not be charmed by his Word, therfore has he <hi>sent serpents and cockatrices among us, that will not be charmed,</hi> (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e threatned, <hi>Ier.</hi> 8.17.) implacable men, that will not heare of Peace. And as at first when Man <hi>divided</hi> from his God, he presently felt a <hi>Division</hi> and Rebellion within himselfe, the inferiour or sensuall denying obedience to the upper part of the soule; so because we have so much fallen off from God and <hi>divided</hi> with him, because from the highest to the lowest of us, there has been such a failing in our duty to our God, therefore doe we now see a <hi>Division</hi> and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in the bowels of the Land: Men risen up that know no Duty, nor acknowledge obedience. What else can we thinke, but that so we have sinned, and so we are punished? Such <hi>Thoughts,</hi> such <hi>searchings of heart</hi> there must be; Thoughts of Wrath; of Wrath for our sinnes, Ours, that thinke perchance we have nothing to answer for in these <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visiont;</hi> and our sinnes, such sinnes especially, as you have heard; <hi>For our Divisions, let there be such thoughts of heart,</hi> Thoughts that make for humiliation.</p>
            <p>In the second place, Thoughts towards God for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting and appeasing of his Wrath; for making up of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:154492:10"/>breach, through which that Wrath has passed upon us, that the <hi>Divisions</hi> also among our selves may be closed up; there is indeed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a great distance that our sinnes have set us at from God, a great gulfe which they have fixed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and us: yet is there inter-course still to be had with Heaven, a passage still for our prayers if sent up with earnest desires, of which this dayes humiliation is the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement. He tels us for our comfort, <hi>Esay</hi> 55.8. <hi>That his thoughts are not as our thoughts,</hi> they are not upon our offences against him, implacable <hi>Thoughts,</hi> as ours are which we have against one another upon our Discords and <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then must our <hi>Thoughes</hi> be of a reunion with God, from whom we have been <hi>divided;</hi> a closing with him, that only can close up our <hi>Divisions;</hi> a making our Peace with him, that only can <hi>make Peace in our borders,</hi> and make them to be of one mind, that have now such disaffected hearts. It is not a joyning with a Forraign Power that can set us streight, not a Covenanting with Brethren of Cruelty, not a League with invading <hi>Svots,</hi> which they have dared to call, <hi>A renewing of Covenant with God;</hi> when as indeed it is no better than a bloody Sacrament, such as <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> Instruments of Cruelty, forced upon the <hi>Sechemites;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 34.</note> or a sacrifice mingled with blood, so much worse than that which <hi>Pilate</hi> marred, <hi>Luke</hi> 13. because they doe it themselves, and with the blood of their Brethren and Fellow Subjects. No way of Peace that: No, it must be a re-union with God a renewing of Covenant with him by new <hi>Thoughts</hi> and resolutions for obedience and amendment, of which this dayes humiliation is the publike profession.</p>
            <p>That this may be done, there must be a <hi>dividing</hi> of the heart from that it cleaves to, when it <hi>divides</hi> from God; it cannot else be re-united to him. This is the <hi>rending of the heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioal 2.</note> requited by the Prophet <hi>Ioel</hi> in our humiliation and returne to God, it must be <hi>rent</hi> and <hi>divided</hi> in it selfe, that's by <hi>contrition,</hi> which breakes the heart in pieces by sorrow, for what is past; <hi>rent</hi> also and <hi>divided</hi> from the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:154492:11"/>creature it cleaves to, that's done by <hi>selfe-deniall,</hi> which takes off the affections from the inordinate love of things below.</p>
            <p>There must be a breaking of the heart for what is past, for it's aversion and <hi>dividing</hi> from God; <hi>Heart-burning Thoughts</hi> there are upon our <hi>Divisions</hi> among our selves, and <hi>Heart-breaking Thoughts</hi> there must be upon our <hi>dividing</hi> from God. The heart so broken in pieces by <hi>Contrition,</hi> may the better every part of it be drawn off from the creature, and by a perfect <hi>selfe-dentall</hi> divided from what it did inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinately cleave to, and so re-united wholly to God: such a <hi>Thought</hi> there must be upon our <hi>Divisions</hi> and Distractions, a <hi>Thought</hi> of re-union with God.</p>
            <p>But not a <hi>Thought</hi> only it must be with full resolution, vowes and purposes; that's the way to fasten the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oule in it's re-union with God, that it may not so easily fall off and <hi>divide</hi> with him againe. It is the <hi>engaging of the heart to approach unto the Lord,</hi> as <hi>Ier.</hi> 30.21. It's the <hi>fixing of the heart</hi> in the Psalmists lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, <hi>My heart is fixed, O God my heart is fixed Psal.</hi> 57.8.</p>
            <p>To bring us to this, it is Gods thought and purpose in the disturbing our quiet and peace by there <hi>Divisions,</hi> that upon the consideration of the uncertaine condition of all things, upon a sense of this <hi>moriens saeculum,</hi> as <hi>Cyprian</hi> calls it, This dying age, these declining times, our heart may think it can fully and finally rest no where but in him. Thus was <hi>David</hi> in the 39 <hi>Psalme, ver.</hi> 6.7. by the sense of his owne frailty and vanity, and of the fading condition of all things else, beaten off from the creature, that he might fasten upon God, as he doth in the next <hi>verse, And now Lord, where is my hope? truely my hope is even in thee.</hi> While our heart is <hi>divided</hi> from God in the pursuit of these outward things, we doe in vaine follow after that which we know not whether we shall enjoy, seeking rest and satisfaction in that which cannot afford it: He therefore now <hi>divides</hi> us from all our pleasant things, puts a stampe of vanity upon them, shewes us how easily they may be taken from us, or we from them, that being beaten off from them by a sense of ours, and their fading uncertaine condition, we may every
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:154492:11"/>one of us returne and say with the Psalmist, <hi>Lord, where is my hope? truly my hope is even in thee:</hi> and, as elsewhere, <hi>My heart is fixed, O God, my heart is fixed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as it is his <hi>Thought</hi> and purpose by these <hi>Divisions</hi> and Disturbances to bring us unto this, so is it what we our selves professe by this dayes Humiliation, if we did but sadly consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what we <hi>desire,</hi> what we <hi>undertake</hi> now at this meeting.</p>
            <p>We <hi>desire</hi> the Lord would wholly remove his judgements from us and come home to us in mercy; should he <hi>divide</hi> with us in his judgements, yea though he gave us the choice, as he did <hi>David,</hi> whether a Famine, or Sword, or Pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, We should thinke our selves in a great strait: Let our Desires then teach us our Duty, and tell us we must not <hi>divide</hi> with Him by our sinfull pleasures, but wholly remove them, and come home to Him.</p>
            <p>And as our Desires may put us upon such <hi>Thoughts</hi> and resolutions, so would our professions this day, if we did but consider what we undertake by our present Humiliation.</p>
            <p>By your fasting your testifie against your soules, that you are displeased with your selves for <hi>dividing</hi> from God, and starting so often from Him to the pleasures of sinne: and therefore you abstaine now and <hi>divide</hi> your selves even from a lawfull use of every thing that may give you ease and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, or refection to Nature; acknowledging thereby your selves unworthy of the comfort of any of Gods creatures, which you have often abused, and unto which your soule has so much cleaved.</p>
            <p>By your presenting your selves before the Lord in this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture of Humiliation, you professe you have entertained bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter purposes and resolutions towards God for the future. You have all of you, I suppose, in your trouble had vowes and purposes of heart for holding closer unto God; I will not examine what fitting <hi>Thoughts</hi> those have beene, how yet unperformed: onely now consider you come to speake them with your mouth, and to professe them openly before the Lord: O let there be <hi>Searchings of hearts</hi> now, that they be answerable to your outward professions
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:154492:12"/>this day, that they be <hi>engaged</hi> to make good what you have now undertaken before the Lord.</p>
            <p>What shall we then say to those we finde desperately <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged</hi> in courses and wayes plainly contrary to the duties which these times, this day requires? Whose hearts are filled with no other <hi>Thoughts,</hi> but those of pleasure, case, pride, and wantonnesse; What will you say, if you see a spot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, painted face upon the day of Humiliation? What can you say, but there's a heart that never <hi>thinkes</hi> of the spots of the soule, a heart so farre from melting, that it may not shed a teare, for feare of spoyling a counterfeit face? If you heare of jollity and musick rioting and excesse, when Gods judgements and publike calamities call for fasting and mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; when <hi>Joseph is grieved</hi> and the cries of the oppressed found in every mans care. What can you say, but Desperate and hard-hearted men, that have no sense of Gods heavy Wrath, but dare thus <hi>provoke the Lord to anger continually to his face?</hi> as he complaines, <hi>Esay</hi> 65.3.</p>
            <p>Should we looke into Taverns and other places of publique receipt, we should finde. I feare, our People often <hi>divided</hi> between them and the Church, and their meeting there to make these Assemblies the lesse. Should we look after many that come up this morne to this place, and observe what they doe when gone from hence, I doubt we should finde they end the Fast with the Sermon; one going to his daily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, and another to his pleasure: What <hi>have ye not houses to eat and drinke in</hi> upon other dayes, that yee never need to runne to the Taverne for the Wine of excesse? And have yee not Chambers and Closets to retire into this day, when yee are gone from hence, there to commune with your hearts, to search them for new thoughts and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutions? We professe to observe a Fast, and <hi>to seek the face of the Lord:</hi> but we seek him, as if we cared not whether we found him; a seeking this of his face? no, its a <hi>provoking of him to his face.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>When I consider what followed on <hi>Jonathans</hi> tasting a little hony within the time appointed for a Fast; although
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:154492:12"/>that Fast was unseasonably enjoyned, and that honey taken by hands that had wrought great deliverance that very day, and tasted by him that was ignorant of the injunction; yet would not the Lord answer because of that trespasse: I trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to thinke how the Lord might answer us in judgement, when as upon the day of Fasting appoynted by like Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and upon better grounds, not onely hands employed to work deliverance, the Souldiers hands are reached out to the honey, the comfort of refection the sweetnesse of sins pleasure this day, but those that scarce lay hand to labor any day, whose usuall employment is case, pleasure, sports and gaming, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abstaine themselves for this time of restraint.</p>
            <p>It is with us as it was with <hi>Moah, Jer.</hi> 48.11. Wee have <hi>beene at ease from our youth,</hi> for many yeares, for a whole age at Peace and undisturbed; but it is worse with us then it was with <hi>Moab</hi> for the ill consequences of our ease and Peace; for therefore did <hi>Moab settle upon his Lees and hold his taste,</hi> because he was <hi>not emptied from vessell to vessell,</hi> never disquicted; but the Lord has shaken and disquieted us, has <hi>emptied us from vessell to vessell,</hi> removed us from Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to Citie, from Country to Country, from our owne hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses to strange habitations; and wheresoever he places us, <hi>we settle on our Lees,</hi> fall upon our wonted pleasures, we will not be <hi>divided</hi> from them, we hold our corrup <hi>taste</hi> still; what remaines, but that the Liquor should be powred out and the vessell broken?</p>
            <p>It is true, that the Lord hath wrought for us many deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances, and that hand of his, which is stretched out for the execution of wrath, hath often reached out unto us the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie; then for the most part, when we had least meanes to at chieve it. Which he has done to witnesse the justnesse of this Cause, and by so many invitations to draw us to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, and a more constant cleaving to him; but to convince our ingratitude and disobedience, he has againe checked out hopes, and given strength againe to the broken Enemie for the continuance of out <hi>Divisions;</hi> and continue they will,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:154492:13"/>so long as we stand so <hi>divided</hi> from him.</p>
            <p>I am no Prophet, to fore-tell what is determined against this Land, but onely tell you what my thoughts are upon our present Condition. When I see on the one side such wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full obstinacie in a seduced People to defend a Cause so ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently unjust: and on the other, that is on our part, such senslessenesse of Gods wrath provoked against this Land, such carelesnesse of using meanes to appease it. I cannot but thinke I see the visible signes of a Nation appointed to destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and must say, it will come to that, if not timely preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>Make the heart of this People fat</hi> (saith the Lord, <hi>Es.</hi> 6.) and <hi>their eares heavy, &amp; their eyes shut;</hi> (such is our condition,) <hi>Then said I, Lord, how long? and he answered me, Till the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties be wasted and the Land desolate.</hi> To that it will come, if our Eyes be not in time opened to see, and our hearts mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified to receive new <hi>impressions</hi> and <hi>thoughts; Impressions</hi> of another stamp, <hi>Thoughts</hi> of another kind, then most men, as it appeares have entertained: Such <hi>Thoughts</hi> and resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as are fit to have, upon a due consideration of these our <hi>Divisions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But persons of publique place must have <hi>Thoughts</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutions for the publique, for reformation of others, as well as themselves. <hi>The Heires of restraint,</hi> (as they are called <hi>Jud.</hi> 18, 7.) not onely to abstaine themselves from what is wicked and prophane, but to represse others also; not onely to be ashamed of doing such things themselves, but to <hi>make others ashamed</hi> for doing so; It is my place and duty to speake it, yours to endeavour it more effectually: You, that have the honour to be called to consult of things making for Peace, and the closing up our <hi>Divisions,</hi> so to move in your severall Spheares, as may be most for the generall benefit. I know not what compasse of Authority you take to move in, but sure I am, you may have a powerfull influence for cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting many distempers amongst us; that there may be a restraint put upon those mouths, that are so often opened in Oathes and Curses: upon those expensive meetings held for
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:154492:13"/>chambering and wantonnesse, excesse and riot in these times of publique wants: upon those many neglects and contempts of this dayes Humiliation, a Duty so necessary for our present Condition. If you take not upon you to command a remedie for all this, yet you can move for it; and then it will appeare (and not till then) that there is a due sense of Gods wrath, when we see Authority effectually engaging it self for redresse of such wicknesse, as doth provoke it.</p>
            <p>And as against prophanenesse of life, so for Religion some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing must be done; the <hi>Vindication</hi> of it was commended to you, when first you were called together, and that not in a Paper, but, as <hi>Joseph</hi> said to his Brethren, ye <hi>saw whose mouth it was,</hi> that spoke it to you; and I speake it againe unto you, not as if Popery were come to a publike Exercise among us, as they falsly report abroad, or as if you should lay violent hands upon our Religion, as they have done: but that something be done to represse the seducing Priest, that is so busie to <hi>divide</hi> our People from us on the one side, and to stop the Calumnies of those seducing Spirits, that carry away the deceived People as madly on the other side.</p>
            <p>Your <hi>Thoughts</hi> and consultations have beene much em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed about the immediate meanes of our safetie: we find the good effect of them, and acknowledge it to your praise; I make no question, but your <hi>hearts</hi> have beene full also of good <hi>Thoughts</hi> and firme resolutions for the established Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and with a little seeking wee may finde them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed in your Declarations: but the businesse deserves something be done on purpose for it, that your Resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may be sufficiently declared, and Authoritie effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally engaged against prophanenesse and superstition, for the advancement of Vertue and Religion.
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 13.</note>
               <hi>Let the Hebrewes heare,</hi> said <hi>Saul,</hi> when hee blew the Trumpet; and let the People abroad heare, say I, what you have done in this particular; and now that the Trumpet is blowne to gather them to Warre, they will come in more readily, and God will sooner give the blessing. You in your place, and everie
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:154492:14"/>man else for his owne part, to entertaine such thoughts and Resolutions upon the Consideration of our <hi>Divisions</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Condition, as may most make for appeasing Gods wrath, and our returne to Him, from whom we have so many wayes <hi>divided.</hi> For the <hi>Divisions</hi> of <hi>Reuben</hi> let there be such <hi>Thoughts</hi> of heart: such <hi>Thoughts</hi> toward God.</p>
            <p>If the breach, which sinne hath made 'twixt God and us, and through which his wrath is powred upon us, were made up, that breach by which we are divided among our selves, and through which we spend our furie one upon another, would not long stand open; But he that has learn't to make his Peace with God (oh that we were come to such a <hi>Thought</hi> and Resolution) must also be carefull how he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haves himselfe towards Men, even those that are Enemies of his Peace; which is the other generall Consideration: Our <hi>Thoughts</hi> towards Man, towards those from whom wee are <hi>divided,</hi> they must be <hi>Thoughts</hi> of Peace, and yet <hi>Resolution</hi> for a necessary Warre.</p>
            <p>First, Thoughts of Peace, even towards them that make ready for Warre; and this is not to weaken your hands, but to set straight your hearts; for that man cannot goe to Warre with a right heart, that has not first the thought of Peace settled in it. The <hi>Samaritan</hi> is propounded to us as an example of spending our Oyle and Wine, and money for the closing up of wounds; A <hi>Samaritan,</hi> one that seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed least concerned to doe it, and to doe it upon a <hi>Jew,</hi> that hated the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> and would have no commerce with them. Had there not beene a Condescention, Heaven and Earth had never met in the Union of reconciliation, nor out Peace with God ever beene made, had not the party offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded sought it.</p>
            <p>While I exhort to this,
<note place="margin">Psal. 34.</note> I speake to your prayse, who have used all faire and honest wayes <hi>to seeke Peace and to pursue it.</hi> And shall I speake what I thinke of the Refufers? It had pleased God by some former successe to heighten them into a contempt of Peace, to thinke all your offers farre below
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:154492:14"/>them, that <hi>he might take them</hi> (as the <hi>Psalmist) in their pride, and make their fiercenesse speake to his prayse.</hi> There wants nothing to the doing of it, but our care to make our Peace with him; and how should our longing after this out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Peace sharpen our desire of that with God and quicken us in the pursuit of it?</p>
            <p>But secondly, If no Peace can be had with the Refufers of Peace but upon unjust tearmes, then must I commend to you other <hi>Thoughts,</hi> to wit, <hi>Resolutions</hi> for a necessarie Warre, and this not to cast out your <hi>thoughts</hi> of Peace, but in order to them; as the Sword must sometimes make the way for Peace, and the readiest meanes to stay blood, is to strike a veine for the letting of it out.</p>
            <p>If you cannot have Peace but upon <hi>Nahash</hi> his Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>to put out your right eyes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 11.</note> and come in blind-fold to them, against your knowledge, against your allegiance: if you cannot yeeld up your selves to their mercie, but you must also yeeld up and sacrifice the Truth to their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice, then learne Resolution in a good Cause from them, that can be so zealous in a bad. They, to joyne Peace and Truth together, can <hi>divide</hi> a Kingdome, a Church, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> They will have no Peace, except their Truthes be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; that you should not thinke of parting with Truth indeed, the ancient received Truth, the established Truth of this Church, to satisfie their unjust demands; but to put on a Resolution at least equall to their boldnesse; I know not how else you will answer the betraying of a just Cause.</p>
            <p>I should not have spoken thus much, though not much, to this point; but that it is too notorious how many, many abroad, many among us have their <hi>hearts di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided</hi> betweene both, and their purses <hi>divided</hi> to uphold both, that they may be safe, as they thinke, which side soever prevaile; such as deserve to be noted as <hi>Reuben</hi> was of great unfaithfulnesse, for holding off in times of distresse.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:154492:15"/>
            <p>It will in the next age stand upon record, who they were <hi>that offered themselves willingly,</hi> as they did, <hi>vers.</hi> 9. <hi>that jeoparded their Irves,</hi> as <hi>Zebulum</hi> and <hi>Nephtali</hi> did, <hi>vers.</hi> 18. So likewise, who they were that stood <hi>divided,</hi> that came not in to the helpe, and so were indeed causes of the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of our <hi>Divisions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, thoughts and resolutions there must be, such as a necessarie Warre requires: and this not to heigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten you into high-swelling <hi>thoughts</hi> of revenge against them you are now <hi>divided</hi> from: no, those are <hi>thoughts</hi> which corrupt nature suggests upon our <hi>Divisions;</hi> but onely to quicken you in the pursuit of that way, which is left you for recovering of your Peace. When once the Sword of Warre (by Gods mercie) shall be sheathed, let no man have a thought of using his owne for private revenge, that no blood be then shed, but what the Sword of Justice shall draw for good example to after Ages. Wee are now though in the posture of Warre, yet in the condition of Suiters, begging for mercie at Gods hands, and can we doe it with reserved thoughts of revenge in our hearts? Wee aske for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givenesse of <hi>Talents,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18.</note> can wee thinke in the meane time of taking our fellow-servants by the throat, when they are in our power, for a few <hi>pence?</hi> There is a satisfaction which the Law may afford, but in case that come not, there is a God to whom Vengeance belongs, and who can make the latter end of every patient <hi>Job</hi> better then the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let your moderation be knowne</hi> (sayth the Apostle) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Phil. 4.5.</note> your equitie, your peaceable disposition: Had that beene in mens hearts, they had not beene so <hi>divided</hi> at this day; And when these <hi>Divisions</hi> shall cease, then also <hi>let your moderation be knowne,</hi> even towards them that have beene Enemies of your Peace, and that because (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle saith) <hi>the Lord is at hand:</hi> the Lord, that came to dye for Enemies, and is comming againe, to take account of your hamelesse behaviour, and shall at that last <hi>Division</hi> se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:154492:15"/>the Goats from the Sheepe; The Goats,
<note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> the Violent ones of this world, how-ever striving here for rule and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence, shall there be put to the left hand; and the Sheepe, the just and peaceable ones, shall follow the Lambe: So hee was called for his innocencie, when hee came to make himselfe a Peace-offering, and so still called through the Booke of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> for the peaceablenesse of his Kingdome: They shall, I say, ever follow the Lambe, never to be <hi>divided</hi> from God and their owne happinesse. Unto that blessed Estate, as our <hi>Thoughts</hi> have beene hitherto directed, in the seeking of a Peace with God and man, so thither let our desires now be raysed in the begging of that Mercie, which onely can close up the breach that our sinnes have made, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>LAUS DEO.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>